Guide to the Aaron Leonard Collection of FOIA Files TAM.762
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Aaron Leonard Collection of FOIA Files
2018-2020
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Leonard, Aaron J.
United States. Federal Bureau of Investigation
TAM.762
7.2 Gigabytes in 166 pdfs
Aaron Leonard is a writer and historian whose primary focus is the history of radicalism and state suppression of radicalism. Leonard is the author of Heavy Radicals: The FBI's Secret War on America's Maoists (2014), A Threat of the First Magnitude: FBI Counterintelligence and Infiltration from the Communist Party to the Revolutionary, 1962-1974 (2017), and The Folk Singers and the Bureau: The FBI, the Folk Artists and the Suppression of the Communist Party, 1939-1956 (2020). The Aaron Leonard Collection of FOIA Files consists of pdfs of declassified Federal Bureau of Investigation documents requested by Leonard through the Freedom of Information Act (FOIA), many of which were obtained as part of his research for The Folk Singers and the Bureau. Materials include pdfs of FBI reports and memoranda on multiple actors, musicians, writers, and composers documenting the subjects' employment, residences, daily activities, travel, and political affiliations, especially any documented or perceived connection to the Communist Party of the United States of America (CPUSA). Subjects of these files include Mary Barnicle, Aaron Copland, Howard Da Silva, Ronnie Gilbert, Archie Green, Marjoie Guthrie, Woody Guthrie, Lee Hays, Fred Hellerman, Cisco Houston, Burl Ives, Aunt Molly Jackson, Millard Lampell, Harold Leventhal, Bess Lomax Hawes, Alan Lomax, Harvey Matusow, Brownie McGhee, Abel Meeropol, Ed Robbin, Suze Rotolo, Pete Seeger, Irwin Silber, Dave Van Ronk, Josh White, and Hally Wood. The files document the federal surveillance of figures in the performing arts during the 1940s and 1950s for evidence of subversive or treasonous actions.
Scope and Contents
The Aaron Leonard Collection of FOIA Files consists of pdfs of declassified Federal Bureau of Investigation documents requested by Leonard through the Freedom of Information Act (FOIA), many of which were obtained as part of his research for The Folk Singers and the Bureau: The FBI, the Folk Artists and the Suppression of the Communist Party, 1939-1956. Materials include pdfs of FBI reports and memoranda on multiple actors, musicians, writers, and composers documenting the subjects' employment, residences, daily activities, travel, and political affiliations, especially any documented or perceived connection to the Communist Party of the United States of America (CPUSA). Subjects of these files include Mary Barnicle, Aaron Copland, Howard Da Silva, Ronnie Gilbert, Archie Green, Marjoie Guthrie, Woody Guthrie, Lee Hays, Fred Hellerman, Cisco Houston, Burl Ives, Aunt Molly Jackson, Millard Lampell, Harold Leventhal, Bess Lomax Hawes, Alan Lomax, Harvey Matusow, Brownie McGhee, Abel Meeropol, Ed Robbin, Suze Rotolo, Pete Seeger, Irwin Silber, Dave Van Ronk, Josh White, and Hally Wood. The files document the federal surveillance of figures in the performing arts during the 1940s and 1950s for evidence of subversive or treasonous actions.
Arrangement
Files are arranged alphabetically by subject's last name.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Aaron Leonard in September 2018, with accretions of files in November 2021 and April 2024; the accession numbers associated with these gift are 2018.123, 2021.076, and 2024.026.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Biographical Note
Aaron Leonard is a writer and historian whose primary focus is the history of radicalism and state suppression of radicalism. Leonard is the author of Heavy Radicals: The FBI's Secret War on America's Maoists (2014), A Threat of the First Magnitude: FBI Counterintelligence and Infiltration from the Communist Party to the Revolutionary, 1962-1974 (2017), and The Folk Singers and the Bureau: The FBI, the Folk Artists and the Suppression of the Communist Party, 1939-1956 (2020). He is also a regular contributor to the History News Network, Truthout, and Jacobin.
Federal government records.; Anti-communist movements -- United States -- 20th century; Communism -- United States -- 20th century; Communism and culture -- United States.; Communism and music -- United States.; Communism and motion pictures -- United States.; Domestic intelligence |z United States.; Folk music.; Folk singers |z United States.; Leonard, Aaron J.; Copland, Aaron, 1900-1990; Da Silva, Howard, 1909-1986; Matusow, Harvey, 1926-2002; Gilbert, Ronnie; Hays, Lee, 1914-1981; Hellerman, Fred, 1927-2016; Houston, Cisco; Ives, Burl, 1909-1995; Jackson, Aunt Molly; Lampell, Millard, 1919-1997; Leventhal, Harold; Hawes, Bess Lomax, 1921-2009; Lomax, Alan, 1915-2002; Meeropol, Abel, 1903-1986; Silber, Irwin, 1925-2010; White, Josh; Communist Party of the United States of America; Barnicle, Mary Elizabeth, 1891-1978; Green, Archie; Guthrie, Marjorie; McGhee, Brownie, 1915-1996; Robbin, Ed; Rotolo, Suze; Van Ronk, Dave; Wood, Hally
- Mary Barnicle, 2024; TW_TAM_762_ER_19
- Richard Dyer Bennett, 2024; TW_TAM_762_ER_20
- Aaron Copland, 2018; cuid34959 (Box Electronic reocrds, E-records TW_TAM_762_ER_1)
- Howard Da Silva, 2018; cuid34960 (Box Electronic reocrds, E-records TW_TAM_762_ER_2)
- Ronnie Gilbert, 2020; cuid34987 (Box Electronic reocrds, E-records TW_TAM_762_ER_4)
- Aaron "Archie" Green, 2024; TW_TAM_762_ER_21
- Marjorie Guthrie, 2024; TW_TAM_762_ER_22
- Woody Guthrie, 2020; cuid34988 (Box Electronic reocrds, E-records TW_TAM_762_ER_5)
- Lee Hays, 2020; cuid34989 (Box Electronic reocrds, E-records TW_TAM_762_ER_6)
- Fred Hellerman, 2020; cuid34990 (Box Electronic reocrds, E-records TW_TAM_762_ER_7)
- Cisco Houston, 2020; cuid34991 (Box Electronic reocrds, E-records TW_TAM_762_ER_8)
- Burl Ives, 2020; cuid34992 (Box Electronic reocrds, E-records TW_TAM_762_ER_9)
- Aunt Molly Jackson, 2020; cuid34993 (Box Electronic reocrds, E-records TW_TAM_762_ER_10)
- Millard Lampell, 2020; cuid34994 (Box Electronic reocrds, E-records TW_TAM_762_ER_11)
- Harold Leventhal, 2020; cuid34995 (Box Electronic reocrds, E-records TW_TAM_762_ER_12)
- Alan Lomax, 2020; cuid34996 (Box Electronic reocrds, E-records TW_TAM_762_ER_13)
- Bess Lomax Hawes, 2020; cuid34997 (Box Electronic reocrds, E-records TW_TAM_762_ER_14)
- Harvey Matusow, 2018; cuid34961 (Box Electronic reocrds, E-records TW_TAM_762_ER_3)
- Brownie McGhee, 2024; TW_TAM_762_ER_23
- Abel Meeropol, 2020; cuid34998 (Box Electronic reocrds, E-records TW_TAM_762_ER_15)
- Ed Robbin, 2024; TW_TAM_762_ER_24
- Suze Rotolo, 2024; TW_TAM_762_ER_25
- Pete Seeger, 2020; cuid34999 (Box Electronic reocrds, E-records TW_TAM_762_ER_16)
- Irwin Silber, 2020; cuid35000 (Box Electronic reocrds, E-records TW_TAM_762_ER_17)
- Dave Van Ronk, 2024; TW_TAM_762_ER_26
- Josh White, 2020; cuid35001 (Box Electronic reocrds, E-records TW_TAM_762_ER_18)
- Hally Wood, 2024; TW_TAM_762_ER_27